Lesson
Simon Collison

The university’s Faculty of Art and Design wasn’t known as the premier art school, and I certainly hadn’t intended to study there. But my first and second choice institutions had refused me, so north I sped, up the A1 to capture my final chance at a fine art degree.

I’d been a studious yet directionless artist, but just recently I’d begun to flirt with abstract painting, which I’d eventually practice with proficiency. Two weeks before my interview, I’d managed to produce three canvases successful enough to ensure my acceptance. I sailed through the inquisition and was offered a place immediately. The following autumn, I left home to study in the North East of England.

My problem at art school, alongside the fact that student hedonism had become for the most part much more important to me than education, was that I drew artistic inspiration from the landscape. The tutors considered this thread of the grand art narrative uncool, imbued with romanticism, and at odds with the trends of the time.

These tutors were an aloof and passionless bunch, clearly more interested in their own flatlining art careers than in molding forty or so dilettantes into worthy professionals. They taught me very little and were dubious and unsupportive of my line of inquiry. One once told me, “You do realize that you’ll never have an exhibition, don’t you?”

Illumination commonly came from the visiting lecturers, many of whom were truly successful in their fields, something I always felt the regular tutors resented. For me, these one-on-one meetings were a rare opportunity to sit with an inspirational figure and dreamily imagine how successful I myself could be in years to come.

One day, a world-renowned, widely respected artist walked into my studio space. At fifty-one years of age, gray and bearded, with a kind yet rugged face, he looked wise and thoughtful and made an instant impression on the twenty-one-year-old me.

This man was Ian Breakwell: diarist, painter, collagist, filmmaker, performer, broadcaster, and writer. He was in the North East fulfilling the prestigious role of artist-in-residence at Durham Cathedral. He was the most accomplished person I’d ever met.

Breakwell was born in Derbyshire, four miles across the county border from where I grew up in Nottinghamshire. He pulled up a chair and sat with me for half an hour, and I recall that we bonded over our similar accent and mild disregard for the insignificant small towns where we each grew up. He then asked me to talk about my work, specifically my direction and motivation.

Initially speaking only occasionally to encourage me, he listened intently, all the while making notes on a scrap of paper.

Breakwell understood that I wasn’t trying to create a romanticized view of the landscape and that my interest was more about journeys, geology, and what we learn about ourselves by immersion in the wilderness.

“What you’re doing is interesting,” he said, as I remember it. “And you should enjoy the fact that it’s at odds with what everyone else in this building is doing.”

This was a significant breakthrough for me. I listened intently as he began to throw more ideas and suggestions my way. Leaning forward as the feedback became increasingly focused, he proffered logical and enlightening suggestions for where I should take my work and how I could draw upon specific influences to better understand my own intentions.

At the end of our meeting, Breakwell passed me the handwritten notes he’d scribbled down. The result was a list of artists whose approaches continue to inspire me today, along with specific references to books and exhibition catalogs. This marked a turning point in my methods of inquiry and thought processes; I learned to narrow my research and to delve deeper into the minds of creative people in order to better understand their own motivations and ways of thinking.

Fast forward to 2003, and after several years of exhibitions and reasonable success, I’d all but abandoned making art as my web career began to flourish. Despite the change of discipline, the way I approach creative output still has its foundations in that meeting almost a decade earlier. In 2005, when I read that Breakwell had died, his passing affected me deeply.

I was, however, delighted to see him receive deserved acknowledgment in the broadsheets. In a thorough obituary for the Independent newspaper, Jeremy Lewison describes Breakwell as a man who “saw the extraordinary in the ordinary.” This was surely meant as a reflection on the artist’s own work, but I like to think this was also something Breakwell hoped to find in the people he encountered. That’s not to say that he considered me extraordinary, but in one short meeting this great man had looked beyond that which others saw and recognized value and potential in what I wanted to achieve.

When I think of such pivotal meetings, they are often serendipitous encounters that continue to resonate with me regardless of where life takes me. They give me guidance that I take everywhere, informing my values and subliminally shaping my choices. Without this collection of lessons, I’d probably be bereft of the motivation and purpose that I hope make me a worthwhile designer at this stage in my life.

The Space Between You and Me Frank Chimero

I fear that we are beginning to design ourselves to suit digital models of us, and I worry about a leaching of empathy and humanity in that process.[1]

— Jaron Lanier

Specks. All of them, even from just seven stories up. We’re on the roof, and you can’t hear what they’re saying. You can’t see what they’re wearing, or the looks on their faces. You can’t see if someone is holding a shopping bag or what may be in it. A red dab follows closely behind a yellow dab. Seven stories up and I can’t tell the difference between a kid being dragged along by his arm and a woman being held at gunpoint for her purse. Distance makes the world blurry. There are no identities. There is no vocabulary. The only language is velocity. They are a school of fish swimming through pavement.

It takes seven stories to strip away the humanity of an individual, 143 steps, each one a degree of separation. No longer people, they are dots on a canvas. Remove a person’s humanity, and she is just a curiosity, a pinpoint on a map, a line in a list, an entry in a database. A person turns into a granular bit of information.

Information can be manipulated. Jesse drapes his head over the lip of the rooftop. He nods and pulls a quarter out of his pocket. He glances back and forth between me and the coin in his hand. He’s looking for permission, and he’s not going to get it from me. He knows that, but it doesn’t matter; he can do what he wants. It’s just information.

Jesse spies an empty parking space directly in front of the building. He presses his middle finger tightly against his thumb with the coin wedged between, and he snaps. The quarter leaps from his hand outward over the street scene, spinning on an invisible axis. Gravity eventually grabs the coin, and it finds its way into the empty parking spot with an assumed rattle and kerrang. Just silence from up here.

Information can be manipulated. Jesse looks at me and nods, this time not for permission, but rather in recognition of what is about to happen. We watch like kids at the aquarium when bait is dropped in the tank. We wait.

The specks on the ground stop. They rotate. The bits bump into one another. Some bits begin to oscillate around the coin’s final landing spot. A small blue dot accelerates toward the coin, then pauses, presumably to pick it up. Behavior has been modified. Jesse looks back at me pleased, as if he were a deity from above, observing how the world reacted when Zeus lazily lobbed his lightning bolt from the mountain top. I imagine the scene from the ground. The bits are looking toward the sky asking, “What the hell was that?”

But Jesse is wrong. We are no gods, and this rooftop is no Olympus. Faith isn’t necessary: they can see us perched on the roof. We are seven stories up; we are hazy specks to them. Jesse is a blue bit, I am red. To them, we are not human. Just information. It only takes seven stories.

A scientist once gave a public lecture on astronomy. He described how the earth orbits around the sun and how the sun orbits around the center of a vast collection of stars called our galaxy.

At the end of the lecture, an elderly woman at the back of the room said, “What you have told us is rubbish. The world is really flat, supported on the back of a giant tortoise.”

The scientist smiled and replied, “What is the tortoise standing on?”

“You’re very clever, young man,” said the old lady. “But it’s turtles all the way down.”

Annie is fidgeting in her office chair at a tiny desk with a monitor on top. We’re sitting in a haphazard home office that looks like it’s been converted from a spare bedroom. “You’ve got to hope there’s someone out there for you, as strange as you are,” she tells me as she pushes her hands through her hair. “And, I don’t know. So much has happened over the past year, and I just need something to go my way for once. I need something good to happen to me, otherwise I’m not sure I can keep going. And…” She looks down and smiles the smallest smile she can make, hoping I won’t notice. “I think this could be it.”

Annie lives at home with her mother, Mary. Mary was a fourth-grade teacher, but her students used to call her Mrs. Blankenship. Some days Mrs. Blankenship can’t remember her own name because she has Alzheimer’s disease. A year and a half ago, Annie’s father died, and her mother’s Alzheimer’s became progressively worse. Annie now lives with her mother in the house she grew up in, tending to the cat and walking the hallways like she’s there by herself. “It’s like living with a ghost,” she says. She is choking up, because she knows that saying that is cruel. Her mother is still here and yet, somehow, not. Earlier, Annie showed me a photo of herself in high school. “It’s embarrassing, really,” she said. “That’s how she sees me.”

Mrs. Blankenship believes that Annie is still sixteen rather than thirty-one. “The situation is really fragile, so I play along. The worst thing would be to make Mom upset.” Annie the thirty-one-year-old has a curfew of nine pm and isn’t allowed to date boys. And that is why we’re sitting at her desk staring at her monitor waiting for something good to happen.

A window pops up on her screen with a ringing sound. Someone is calling Annie. “This could be it,” I say to myself. It’s Brandon and I excuse myself from the room to wander the halls as Mrs. Blankenship sleeps in the next room. The cat rubs against my leg.

Later that night, Annie introduces me to Brandon over the computer, and he and I make plans to get together for coffee at his place the next day. Brandon has an apartment in the city thirty minutes away and a job working as a legal assistant. He tells me he met Annie on a dating website eight weeks ago. “There’s a certain guilt browsing a dating website because for it to be useful you just have to say no over and over.” I nod but don’t say anything in the hope that he’ll add more. An awkward silence.

“Under 5’2”? No. Blonde? No. No college degree? No. There’s a ticker at the bottom of the page that shows how many results come back after the filter. Mine said about 2,000. Two thousand people I could love. Probably 14,000 more that it didn’t even show me. And yet still, these are all people. They are all looking back, and they want the same thing I do." He looks down at his black coffee and I notice that he can see himself in it.

“What do they want, Brandon?”

He pauses a moment to think. “To be understood.”

Brandon scrolls through the webpage for me, and it is overwhelming: a cascade of smiles, an immense tide of humanity that goes on forever. The distance makes you forget that these are real people, not just pictures. They secretly love something they can’t tell anyone about. They live for the moment they hold their breath and submerge their head in a warm bath. They are human. On the site, each and every person in the grid of faces has a smile that admits, “I am not yet done.”

I have to shut myself off. My heart is not big enough to hold them all.

“Have you heard the joke about the astronomer’s lecture and the turtle?” Brandon asks.

“Yeah, turtles all the way down, right?” I reply.

“Yes. Scrolling through this page, I never realized it before, but the web. It’s just people all the way down, isn’t it?”

I hadn’t thought of it. The best sorts of insights are like that. When you hear them, they seem so obvious, but until someone says them out loud, they are almost unthinkable.

Let’s just try to have a marvelous time this weekend. I mean not try to analyze everything to death for once, if possible. Especially me. I love you.[2]

— Franny

A network is a connection of nodes. The history of our network has been a study in how the edges have pushed further out. First our network was for small bits of data transmission. It was for correspondence: short, awkward messages of text sent mostly to people you didn’t know. They were the only people out there; the only nodes who could signal us back, who could answer. Then, the edges pushed out, and the network could share images, and then it crept into other media.

Every shared item became replicated. A full and perfect copy of the content was produced every time it changed hands. All of the copies filled up the room and made waves of content that could be surfed. Then, the network became social. The nodes started talking to one another in much the same way they did outside of the network, and we created a world parallel to that of the real fabric that joined the nodes in physical space.

The nodes are not technology. The web is not an interlinking of servers and scripts. Each node is a person. Tanya checks her email on her phone and gets a message from her sister. Brad is the systems admin guy who turns on the oscillating fans in the server room. Qian assembles an iPhone at the Foxconn plant in Shenzen. Shannon writes something for her employer’s website. Tim curses because he can’t find what Shannon wrote. Larry and Sergey make a website so people like Tim can find the things that people like Shannon make. Every little bit that gets pushed through the network passes through a person. The web is technology, but more importantly, it is people, all the way down. People constitute and maintain the network. It is widespread and distributed, but it is very delicate. Like a real web, it needs constant maintenance to keep from tearing.

Technology is a mirror and a crystal ball. The web is a reflection of our desires because it addresses our needs en masse. It is a documentation of how we try to fix ourselves, a study in our self-medication. The web is also a crystal ball because it presents what is to come. Technology is produced to fill our needs, but we are sympathetic creatures. Frequently, we will reduce our needs to feel that the technology is properly serving us, in spite of the inadequacies of the solutions. A half answer is better than nothing at all, and we wish to be satisfied with the solutions at hand, so we shallow our problems, losing sight of their original depth. We shape technology, and it shapes us.

And so our relationship with the social web has gone thus far. It seems silly to say that a network of people may induce person-blindness, but it can and does each day. If the web is a representation of the fabric of humanity, it is a thin veil draped over all of us. The way the web is currently wired accidentally strips the nodes of their personhood because of distance and turns them into odd, person-like entities. Jesse flings his coin from the rooftop.

It is a struggle to stay human online: avatars of logos (or the very term avatar); the phrase personal brand; descriptions of the whole of your existence in a little flashing, empty box labeled About Me. The social networks that connect us as people accidentally reduce us. Odd that the totality of a person’s profile need be described through a list of favorite books, movies, and quotes. Is what I like more important than what I think or what I make or who I love? Is it that people aren’t willing to describe themselves as people online. Or is it that we aren’t providing a suitable framework for them to do so? We perceive the situation to be technology mirroring our disposition, but it is more a shallowing of ourselves via the crystal ball.

When the nodes cease to be human, we respond differently. A person with reasons becomes a detached opinion that is wrong; actions become annoyances to lash out against; the personality of an individual becomes a brand without context. Can providing the human element to the web alleviate these problems? The web documents and doesn’t forget, but if users turn into people, can we forgive? Forgiveness is a term I’ve never heard in relation to the web. Let’s not try to analyze everything to death for once. Especially me. I love you.

The connections we make in the course of a life — maybe that’s what heaven is, Tom. We make so many connections here on earth. Look at us — I’ve just met you, but I’m investing in who you are and who you will be, and I can’t help it.

— Fred Rogers (Mr. Rogers)[3]

When the network became social, it was dumb. It lacked nuance. The social network was based on our idea of ourselves and technology. When we think of ourselves, we picture our complex inner monologues: we believe that we are not simple but rather complex, romantic, self-contradicting — beautiful messes. We say this is what makes us human. But what if we’re wrong? What if we pull back the veil to discover that perhaps we are not so complex, but instead we are the opposite?

Technology runs counter to our personhood; technology is complicated and shallow, but people are simple and deep. Our true needs are not complex. I remembered asking Brandon what everyone needed. His answer was profound and human: “To be understood.”

The most exceptional inventions forecast our needs and allow us to realize our full potential. They bring us joy and a sense of brilliance; they make us feel skilled, competent, and more able. Good technology makes us feel like we are inching closer to who we truly want to be. The web has done much to improve our lives, and now it turns its head toward our emotional needs. If it does its job, it can help us to get to Brandon’s idea of being understood: that cyclical process of empathy where one may feel seen, known, and accepted by others, then able to feel the same for them.

Art is the first man-made conduit to this cycle of understanding. The measure of an artist is his ability to place his finger on the face of a feeling; a masterpiece acts as a lens whose focus crystallizes our selves, one another, the world. Can our social network achieve the same? Are our tools adequate for a true art of conversation? Most importantly, have we produced a proper representation of humanity for these conversations or a simplified facsimile?

Anything good we may do with this network must be built in a way that utilizes the fabric that binds us, that brings us closer so that our humanness may snap back into focus by eliminating distance. We are all swaddled in the same blanket. By recognizing that, we inch closer to being understood.

We might forget too easily that these nodes, these usernames, are in fact people. People deserve more than the term username; they’ve earned a richer biography than a series of labels or a list of favorite movies. We must not allow interactions online to be perpetually stuck in the conversational depth of a first date. We can shun complex and shallow and embrace simple and deep.

We are not there, and yet, I have hope. We can make conduits for meaningful relationships, like the one Annie and Brandon might have. We can feel understood. Jesse and I can come down from the roof. We may empathize and be closer. We, the makers and form-givers of these new technologies, can look someone in the eye and ask “How can I make things that help you to be who you truly want to be?”

See, I’ve just met you, but I am invested in who you are. We are part of a human network. Maybe that’s heaven.

Jaron Lanier, You Are Not a Gadget: A Manifesto, (Vintage Books, 2011). ↩

JD Salinger, Franny and Zooey, (Little, Brown and Company, 1961). ↩

Tom Junod, “Can You Say…Hero?” (Esquire, November, 1998). ↩

Lesson Jon Tan

It’s an age ago. I’m on a beach called Haad Rin Nok, on an island called Kho Pha Ngan in the Gulf of Thailand. The beach is deep, pale sand bounded by green steep headlands to the north and south, the sea in front, and wooden bars and bungalows behind.

There’s a Full Moon Party tonight.

It’s almost dark. Music is everywhere. The beaches and bars are scattered with backpackers. To the south is a small bar with a sand floor, tables running down the right, the bar to the left. It’s almost empty. That’s why I walked in.

Except it’s not quite empty. Four Thai men sit around a table. They’re slender and trim, slightly smaller than Europeans the way most Thai people are. Sweating bottles of Chang beer sit in front of them. One man has a long ponytail tied neatly back. His elbows rest on the table as he softly spits quick-fire whispers across it, punctuated with small emphatic gestures as tightly contained as the volume of his tirade. As he speaks he stares intently at the man opposite him, who hunches forward into this storm, arms tucked between his legs, leaving the table to the speaker in an unconscious act of submission. I notice all this in a glance and raise an eyebrow at the barman who returns the smallest of shrugs.

Thai people are renowned for their friendliness. Travel companies describe Thailand as a happy place, “the land of smiles.” That trite message completely misses the array of emotions a smile in Thailand can convey other than happiness. The barman doesn’t smile. Suddenly I’m very wary.

Into the bar bounds a Western guy just getting started on his backpacking adventure, to judge by his pasty skin. He’s leaking exuberance in anticipation of the night ahead. He’s massive. Six-and-a-half feet tall with shoulders like beer kegs, and full of friendly energy. He orders a handful of beers and with a broad grin notices the guys around the table as the barman reaches back for them. Just at that moment the speaker pokes a finger in the air as he snaps angrily at his counterpart. The backpacker’s grin doesn’t falter. “Hey guys, c’mon, don’t argue!” he shouts in response.

The guys at the table ignore him without a glance or breaking their conversation.

I try to catch his eye, but he’s already moving over to them. Not used to being ignored, and with an absolute confidence in his presence and the certainty that his good humor is infectious, he feels a sense of righteousness that carries him on in his intervention.

“Hey! C’mon, man” he scolds with a grin. “Quit arguing, dude. It’s the Full Moon Party!”

The table goes silent. The speaker looks up.

The backpacker pauses. Emboldened by finally managing to attract their attention, he throws his huge arms wide in a gesture of invitation. “Hey! C’mon, man, have a dr…”

In a flash, the speaker lunges out of his seat, smashes a bottle of Chang in hand, and pursues the backpacker onto the beach at top speed. The table empties as the other three guys and I follow.

The backpacker tears up the beach at breakneck speed, terror on his face as he casts frantic glances over his shoulder at the speaker flying a few strides behind, broken bottle pumping in his fist. Violent intent rolls off him in waves. The two disappear into the distance. The only indication of where they are is the herd of people craning their necks then stepping back as they run by. People are shouting now. The runners are heading back toward us. Some people laugh. There’s dark humor in the laughter. A tiny, murderous-looking Thai man is chasing one of the largest backpackers they’ve ever seen. The backpacker isn’t laughing. He’s running for his life, and on his face is the absolute certainty of knowing that the guy behind him isn’t laughing either.

They draw level with the bar; the backpacker is fading fast, and the speaker is closer. In a spray of sand, the backpacker sprawls to his knees, turns, and faces his pursuer. His mouth is open, chest sucking air, massive arms held in front of him, palms up. Eyes wide with fear.

“Sorry, man. Sorry! Please, I didn’t mean anything. Nothing. Sorry. Please!”

The speaker halts in front of him. He’s looking down, face twisted with rage, bottle loose in his fist, the jagged edges raw and dark. He glances at the group standing in front of the bar. Then he smiles.

The backpacker’s face rises from fear to relief.

But then the bottle is pressing against his neck. The speaker’s smile has gone. The backpacker freezes. People including me shout, “No!”

The speaker smiles again. He steps back, clips the backpacker around the ear and, still smiling, drops the bottle and walks back into the bar. His friends follow. I’m watching the backpacker, slumped on the sand, tears in his eyes. We help him up. He’s in shock, too ashamed to speak or look anyone in the eye, and mutters he’s fine as he stumbles away. I am shaking, too.

The sun went down fast. In the dark that night, as the music thumped and the SangSom flowed on the beach, my friends and I relived this most savage lesson. I couldn’t condone what the speaker did, but I understood him. He could not lose face in front of his peers. He wasn’t looking for trouble; it just walked up to his table. I also understood how a Westerner might expect a positive response to a friendly, good-humored scolding. The backpacker learned that in Thai society, some people will go to extraordinary lengths to save face. I learned that the world may seem small, but our cultural differences can be vast. Try to understand people, lest they surprise you with their smiles.

Authors

Frank Chimero

Frank Chimero is a designer, writer, illustrator, and educator. He is interested in aesthetics, chance, culture, language, process, style, automation, design, seeing, perception, wit, typography, wordplay, identity, form, paradigms, and the tools, symbols, style, future. He is happiest when he forgets himself.

Simon Collison

Simon is a UK-based web designer with over a decade of experience at the sharp end. Simon cofounded the successful Erskine Design which he ran for four years before returning to freelancing. He’s written a few books and speaks about design at events around the world. Simon also organizes the New Adventures conference, is working on a new book, and some ambitious top-secret projects.

Liz Danzico

Liz Danzico is part educator, part designer, part editor, and full-time dog owner, who writes part of her time at Bobulate. After more than a decade, she still finds it lovely to live and work in New York City.

Dan Rubin

Dan Rubin is a man of many interests and talents. A designer, photographer, and barbershop harmony aficionado, he speaks at conferences around the world, writes about myriad topics, and works with good-looking clients including MailChimp, Google,Yahoo!, Microsoft, Geffen/Universal, and IDEO.

Jon Tan

Jon is a designer. He cofounded Fontdeck, and the Analog cooperative, where he works with friends creating things like the new Mapalong web app, and running the Brooklyn Beta conference. Jon speaks internationally, and writes about design and typography. When he’s not traveling, Jon’s base is the co-working studio, Mild Bunch HQ, run by Analog in Bristol, UK.

The Standardistas

Christopher Murphy and Nicklas Persson teach interactive design at the University of Ulster at Belfast, where they have been active in promoting a web standards-based curriculum. As the tweed-clad duo, The Standardistas, they write and speak regularly on standards-based web design. They’ve written for 24 Ways, New Adventures, and .net magazine, and a book, HTML and CSS Web Standards Solutions: A Web Standardistas’ Approach.

Illustrators

Raymond Biesinger

Raymond Biesinger is a multitalented illustrator whose headquarters is Montreal, Canada. He’s drawn for everyone from the New Yorker to little photo copied zines, and he’s now working on prints, books, and an instructional audio LP.

Owen Gatley

Owen hails from the Malvern Hills in Worcestershire and likes to create playful illustrations, often taking inspiration from 1950s color palettes and comic books. Clients include Pan Macmillan, Urban Outfitters, and The Times.

Christopher Gray

Christopher Gray is a graphic designer based in Sweden. In 2009 he started the Illustration label Toy and is represented by animation film company Studio AKA. His work uses a minimalist style to convey thoughts, narratives, and concepts. His work has been published by Die Gestalten, Creative Review, idN, and Wallpaper*. In the past year he has collaborated with the BBC, Nike, Moleskine, and the New York Times.

Superbrothers

Superbrothers, Inc. is an ambiguously pluralized art and design organization located in Toronto committed to creating audiovisual ephemera for a broad, literate audience. They are the co-creators of the the archetypical adventure videogame project for iOS known as Sword & Sworcery.

Olimpia Zagnoli

OZ was born in 1984. OZ is an illustrator. OZ lives in Milan. OZ loves New York. OZ listens to T. Rex. OZ eats popcorn. OZ reads Peanuts. OZ drives a Yellow Fiat. OZ is Olimpia Zagnoli.

Ping Zhu

Ping is an illustrator organically grown in Los Angeles and imported to London. She loves animals and speed drawing on Post-its®.When feeling fancy, she combines them.